Guide to the James R. Dumpson Papers circa 1922-2015 MS 3078
New-York Historical Society
James R. Dumpson papers
circa 1922-2015
New-York Historical Society
Dumpson, James R., 1909-2012
MS 3078
22.82 Linear Feet (in 22 record cartons and 2 document boxes).
Speeches, conference papers, correspondence, scrapbooks, and publications of James R. Dumpson (1909–2012), New York City Commissioner of Welfare (1959–1965). When appointed Dumpson was the first African American welfare commissioner in the United States, and the first social worker to oversee welfare in New York. He later served as Dean of Fordham University's Graduate School of Social Service (1967–1974), and Administrator of New York City's Human Resources Administration (1974–1976). The collection includes material from Dumpson's time as United Nations Advisor and Chief of Training in Social Welfare to the Government of Pakistan (1953–1954), and from his work in South Vietnam during the 1960s and 1970s for the U.S. Senate Sub-Committee on Refugees and Escapees.
Arrangement
The James R. Dumpson Papers are organized in nine series:
Series I. Speeches, articles, papers, remarks, 1932-2005
Series II. Correspondence, 1930-2008
Series III. Memorabilia and Scrapbooks, 1928-2009
Series IV. Personal, 1950s-2012
Series V. Fordham University, 1965-1996
Series VI. International Social Welfare, 1952-2001
Series VII. Miscellaneous files, binders, and loose material, circa 1930-2015
Series VIII. Print matter, 1922-2009
Series IX. Audiovisual, 1946-1992
Biographical Note
Nicknamed "Little Dynamo" for the boundless enthusiasm contained by his diminutive frame, James Russell Dumpson (1909–2012) was, among his many roles, the first African American welfare commissioner in American history. Born in Philadelphia on 5 April 1909, Dumpson was the oldest of the five children of James T. Dumpson (1884–1934), a bank messenger, and Edythe (Smith) Dumpson (1892–1944), who taught public school before her marriage.
After high school, Dumpson attended State Teachers College at Cheyney, Pennsylvania (1930–1932), the University of Pennsylvania School of Social Work (1937–1938), and Fordham University School of Social Service (1942–1944). He obtained bachelor's (1947) and master's (1950) degrees from the New School for Social Research before completing a Ph.D. at the University of Dacca, East Pakistan (1955). Dumpson was already working in Pakistan (1953–1954), where he had been appointed United Nations Advisor and Chief of Training in Social Welfare to the country's then newly-formed government.
Back in New York City he served as Director, Bureau of Child Welfare, in the Department of Welfare (1955–1958), and then as First Deputy Commissioner of Welfare (1958–1959). When Mayor Robert F. Wagner Jr. appointed Dumpson the City's Commissioner of Welfare (1959–1965), he became the first African American to hold such a position in the United States. He was also the first trained social worker to oversee welfare in New York, and, as such, took exception to a Daily News editorial which attributed the City's welfare woes to ladies having "babies by assorted gentlemen so as to keep the relief checks growing fatter each year." Dumpson responded that the "only test for public assistance was a citizen's needs, not morals. With only a few exceptions... people on welfare, particularly children, desperately need the support." In 1964, after Senator Barry Goldwater of Arizona had similarly disparaged welfare recipients, Dumpson referred to the soon-to-be Republican nominee for president as "the wealthy cowboy," dismissing his remarks as having "no place in the kind of war on poverty I am advocating."
Leaving the municipal sphere, Dumpson was briefly (1965–1967) professor and associate dean of the Hunter College School of Social Work before assuming deanship of Fordham University's Graduate School of Social Service (1967–1974). In his honor, the school would name the "James R. Dumpson Chair in Child Welfare Services" in 1980.
Mayor Abraham Beame lured Dumpson back to public service, appointing him Administrator of the New York City Human Resources Administration and Commissioner of the Department of Social Services (1974–1976).
At a time when less driven humans might have retired, Dumpson actively consulted or sat on—and often chaired—a dizzying number of charitable and philanthropic boards. In his 80s he was tapped by Mayor David Dinkins to oversee the New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation.
James R. Dumpson died in New York City on 5 November 2012, aged 103, survived by his widow, Goldie (Brangman) Dumpson, the former director of a nurse anesthesia program New York, and his daughter, the psychotherapist Jeree Wade.
[The most detailed chronology of Dumpson's life and work appears in Alma J. Carten, Reflections on the American Social Welfare State: The Collected Papers of James R. Dumpson, PhD, 1930-1990 (Washington, D.C.: National Association of Social Workers Press, 2015), 233–236. A photocopy may be found in box 6, folder 14. See also "Friend to the Needy: James Russell Dumpson," in the New York Times, 18 July 1959, and "James R. Dumpson, a Defender of the Poor, Dies at 103," also in the New York Times, 9 November 2012.]
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeree Wade, daughter of James R. Dumpson, 2017.
Related Materials
The Fordham University Library Archives holds a significant collection of James R. Dumpson's papers (11 linear feet in 13 boxes). As of this writing (March 2019), Fordham's online finding aid [http://www.library.fordham.edu/archives/dumpsonpapers.html] is not functioning, but a copy saved by the Internet Archive Wayback Machine remains visible. (Paper copies may also be found in the present, New-York Historical Society, collection, in box 6, folder 14.)
Scope and Contents
The James R. Dumpson Papers span Dr. Dumpson's long and busy working life—he remained active into his tenth decade—in the field of social welfare both at home and abroad. The collection includes a dizzying number of speeches, conference papers, and articles, not to mention the contributions Dumpson made to various publications. (See Series I and Series VIII.)
Dumpson's correspondence, while spread throughout the collection, is spotty, and grouped largely in nine folders covering the years 1930–2008. Of interest are the letters he received as New York City's Commissioner of Welfare, when social workers of his department staged a month-long strike for better pay and more manageable caseloads in January 1965. (See Series II.)
The collection includes a large amount of "memorabilia" (Dumpson's designation) that was originally stored in binders and in scrapbooks, a mixture of ephemera, correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and publications documenting Dumpson's educational, professional, and private life. (See Series III.)
Personal material is limited to a few financial papers and receipts, citations, and a folder of photographs of Dumpson, either solo portraits, or posed with New York City officials and visiting dignitaries, at casual functions and award ceremonies. (See Series IV.)
From his tenure as dean of Fordham University's Graduate School of Social Service, the collection holds a mix of correspondence, administrative memos, accreditation reports, and information on the naming of a chair in his honor in 1980—the James R. Dumpson Chair in Child Welfare Services. (See Series V.)
Dumpson's international social welfare activities are documented by material from his time during the 1950s as United Nations Advisor and Chief of Training in Social Welfare to the then newly-formed Government of Pakistan, and his work during the 1960s and 1970s for the United States Senate Sub-Committee on Refugees and Escapees in South Vietnam. (See Series VI.)
The collection contains a number of single-topic files—such as those covering Dumpson's time as administrator of the New York City Human Resources Administration—and a significant amount of loose and unlabeled material that defies precise categorization, but relates broadly to the perennial issues of social welfare. (See Series VII.)
Dumpson assembled a range of printed publications—books, pamphlets, periodicals, government documents, and conference proceedings—many of which include chapters or prefatory contributions by him. While most publications in the collection center on social welfare generally, some focus on specific issues like aging, or black children in foster care. And some, such as a 1922 monograph on Renaissance art and poetry, seem to date from Dumpson's school days. (See Series VIII.)
Lastly, a small amount of phonograph and VHS recordings capture Dumpson's appearances on New York City-based radio and television broadcasts discussing, among other topics, juvenile delinquency, the AIDS crisis, and homelessness. (See Series IX.)
Researchers should be aware that the Fordham University Library Archives holds a significant collection of James R. Dumpson's papers (11 linear feet in 13 boxes). As of this writing (March 2019), Fordham's online finding aid [http://www.library.fordham.edu/archives/dumpsonpapers.html] is not functioning, but a copy saved by the Internet Archive Wayback Machine remains visible. (Paper copies may also be found in the present, New-York Historical Society, collection, in box 6, folder 14.)
Public welfare -- Pakistan; Public welfare -- United States; Public welfare -- Vietnam; Schools of social work; Social service -- United States; Social work administration -- United States; Correspondence.; Phonograph records; Photographs; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); VHS (TM); Fordham University. Graduate School of Social Service; National Conference of Social Work (U.S.). Annual Conference; New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation; New York (N.Y.). Department of Social Services; New York (N.Y.). Human Resources Administration; State Teachers College at Cheyney
- Series I. Speeches, articles, papers, remarks, reviews, etc., 1932-2005; 2.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Series I holds the myriad conference papers, speeches, articles, remarks, and reviews delivered by James R. Dumpson throughout his long and ever-evolving career in social work.
  Arrangement
  Series I is sorted chronologically. Undated items come last. The researcher may encounter duplication of papers revised for publication, or presented in multiple forums.
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1932, 1938 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    The Educated Man in the Time of Depression (30 May 1932).
    The Administration of Public Assistance and its Relationship to Pressure Groups (December 1938).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    The Child and His Family During the Period of Foster Care (27 October 1944).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1951 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    The Menace of Narcotics to the Children of New York: A Plan to Eradicate the Evil (August 1951).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1955-1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Statement, dedication of cottage at St. Agatha's, Nanuet, New York (22 April 1955).
    What is Happening to Our Children Overseas? (29 March 1957).
    Improving Social Relations, Developing Social Responsibility, and Enrichment of Life (23 September 1957).
    Governmental Responsibility on the Mobilization of Resources for Program Planning and Development of the Social Services (October 1957).
    Organized Guidance of the Family for its Socio-Economic Development (9 April 1958).
    Exploring New Horizons: A Challenge to the Status Quo (26 April 1958).
    Community Organization Responsibility of the Public Administrator (12 May 1958).
    Relationships With Public Agencies for Children (22 May 1958).
    How High the Ceiling (4 June 1958).
    Philosophy, Convictions and Goals in Public Welfare (17 October 1958).
    Teamwork Among Community Agencies for the Mentally Ill (30 October 1958)
    Recent Developments in Public Services for Families (17 November 1958).
    Public and Private Agency Responsibility (19 November 1958).
    Are Residence Laws Necessary? (17 March 1959).
    Serving the Multi-Problem Family: Implications for the Public Agency (1 April 1959).
    How to Establish Community Programs: Special Problems and Needs of the Aging Among the Minority Groups (16 April 1959).
    Public Welfare and Community Planning (9 September 1959).
    "ADC and Human Rights" by Dean Wayne Vasey, discussed by James R. Dumpson (22 September 1959).
    The Future of Public Welfare in New York City (19 October 1959).
    A Changing City: New Issues and New Relationships (8 November 1959).
    Public Welfare and the Newcomer (3 December 1959).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    A New Look at Medical Welfare in New York City (15 March 1960).
    Mobility and Health and Living Conditions as These Affect the Young (28 March 1960).
    Commencement address, State Teachers College, Cheyney, Pennsylvania (23 March 1960).
    Speech on child welfare (26 May 1960).
    Working Together on Old Problems in Child Welfare (9 June 1960).
    Why Public Welfare is Everyone's Concern: A Statement of Philosophy, Convictions and Goals in Public Welfare (23 June 1960).
    The Next Twenty-Five Years in Public Welfare (9 September 1960).
    National Health and Welfare Needs and Programs (29 September 1960).
    The Place of Public Welfare in an Affluent Society (2 October 1960).
    Welfare Services - Private and Public Potentials from a Public Agency Point of View (26 October 1960).
    "A Challenge of Service: Current Developments in Staff Training in Public Assistance" by Hilda Tebow, discussed by James R. Dumpson (5 November 1960).
    Statement... to the Subcommittee on Public Welfare of the Temporary State Commission on Coordination of State Activities (14 November 1960).
    The Welfare of Children is Everybody's Business. "Hindrances, Obstacles and Bottlenecks to a Good Program" (30 November 1960).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    The Next Twenty-Five Years in Public Welfare (19 January 1961).
    Can We Afford Unmet Human Needs? (25 January 1961).
    Statement on Child Welfare (1 February 1961).
    Facts, Fallacies and Future: A Study of the Aid to Dependent Children Program of Cook County, Illinois (23 February 1961).
    The Unmarried Mother and the ADC in New York City (25 March 1961).
    Maladjustment Among Children (13 April 1961).
    Protecting Our Children (17 April 1961).
    Report to Asia Foundation of Assignment in Pakistan (April 1961).
    Working Together in Behalf of Children (10 May 1961).
    Hunger and Human Welfare at Home and Abroad (16 May 1961).
    Statement at Conference of Greater New York Negro American Labor Council (10 June 1961).
    A New Look at Medical Welfare in New York City (12 June 1961).
    Working Together for Children (14 June 1961).
    Emerging Needs, Trends and Issues in Medical Care (3 October 1961).
    Myths and Misunderstandings About Public Welfare (26 October 1961).
    Public and Voluntary Agency Partnership Responsibilities (30 October 1961).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Child Welfare: Whose Responsibility[?] (17 January 1962).
    Public and Voluntary Agency Partnership Responsibilities (January 1962).
    The ADC Family in the World of Today (1 March 1962).
    Keynote Statement, Seminar on Harlem Youth Needs (20 March 1962).
    Improving the Living of Children and Their Families (27 March 1962).
    United States Social Work in International Community Development (9 April 1962).
    A Program for Raising Minimum Wages and Lowering Welfare Costs (24 April 1962).
    Human Welfare in the Next Decade (28 April 1962).
    Day Care Week--Remarks at Annual Luncheon (30 April 1962).
    New York Hospital--Welfare Project (15 May 1962).
    How Efficiently are We Spending Public and Private Funds to Meet Family and Child Welfare Needs? (25 May 1962).
    Public-Private Agency Relationship (25 May 1962).
    Public Welfare Revisited: 1962 (Suggestions for Mayor Wagner's Address) (27 May 1962).
    Introduction of Honorable Robert F. Wagner, Mayor, City of New York (27 May 1962).
    Public Welfare Today--Implications of Current Developments for Services to the Aging (29 May 1962).
    Leadership and Problems of Negro Family Disorganization (31 May 1962).
    Crisis in the Metropolis and Intergroup Relations (5 June 1962).
    Preventive and Restorative Services--Key to Public Welfare's Future (14 September 1962).
    Grosvenor Neighborhood House--Cornerstone Ceremony (Comments) (17 October 1962).
    Public Welfare Revisited (1 November 1962).
    Voluntary-Public Partnerships in Programming for the Aged (8 November 1962).
    Public Welfare Revisited (15 November 1962).
    Statement before the Joint Legislative Committee on Health Insurance Plans (16 November 1962).
    Challenge to Public Welfare in the 60's--Implications for Welfare Administrators (29 November 1962).
    Impact of Automation on Welfare (10 December 1962).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. [part 1], 1963 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Public and Voluntary Agency Partnership Responsibilities (25 January 1963).
    How Efficiently are we Spending Public and Private Funds to Meet Welfare Needs? (5 February 1963).
    The Local Outlook (Notes) (5 March 1963).
    A Consideration: The General Welfare (13 March 1963).
    Statement on Morland Commission Report (at Common Council) (14 March 1963).
    Purchase of Care--Issues at Stake (25 April 1963).
    Public Welfare: Today and Tomorrow (29 April 1963).
    Place of Child Day Care in Meeting Children's Needs (1 May 1963).
    Greetings, Angel Guardian Home Smoker (2 May 1963).
    Public and Private Agency Responsibilities (12 May 1963).
    Statement, Department of Welfare Symposium in Brooklyn (8 May 1963).
    A Changing World--A Changing Profession (notes) (13 May 1963).
    Notes on Public Welfare (for Graduate Seminar on Social Welfare Administration) (13 May 1963).
    Outline for Leadership Workshop on Children's Needs (10 June 1963).
    Statement at Public Hearing of Joint Legislative Committee on Health Insurance Plans (10 June 1963).
    Challenge to Public Welfare in the 60's--Its Public Image (18 June 1963).
    Social Welfare Problems and Needs (20 June 1963).
    Statement--Memorial Meeting for Medgar W. Evers (27 June 1963).
    Article on Public Assistance (Encyclopedia of Social Work) (June 1963).
    The Public Welfare Amendments of 1962--Their Implications (August 1963).
    Operation Alphabet (17 September 1963).
    Urban Renewal's Challenge to Social Welfare (23 September 1963).
    Remarks at Hearing on Rehabilitation Report of the City Planning Commission (24 September 1963).
    New Directions in Catholic Child Care (28 September 1963).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. [part 2], 1963 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Automation--A Community Reponsibility: The Meaning of Automation to the Public Welfare Administrator (9 October 1963).
    Why Public Welfare[?] (24 October 1963).
    Statement before the Temporary State Commission on Low Income Housing (29 October 1963).
    Remarks at Donor Dinner of Wiltwyck School for Boys (30 October 1963).
    Statement at Luncheon--Manhattan Chapter, Childville (and Transcript of Interview on WNYC) (12 November 1963).
    Philosophical Tenets Underlying Administration of New York City Department of Welfare (15 November 1963).
    Translating Knowledge into Local and State Action (18 November 1963).
    Statement at Day Care Council Annual Meeting (18 November 1963).
    Notes on Types of Public Funding (20 November 1963).
    Automation--A Community Responsibility (4 December 1963).
    AFDC: Facts vs. Fiction (as Discussant) (5 December 1963).
    The Social Impact of Automation (6 December 1963).
    Emerging Horizons in Human Rights and Minority Groups (10 December 1963).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. [part 1], 1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    The Efficient Spending of Public and Private Funds to Meet Social Welfare Needs in a Large Metropolitan Community (also notes based on above paper) (7 January 1964).
    Some Crucial Issues in Child Welfare (21 January 1964).
    The Second Vatican Council: Its Meaning for Mankind (20 February 1964).
    Notes for Workshop on Poverty (7 March 1964).
    Implications of the 1962 Public Welfare Amendments (notes-NASW) (19 March 1964).
    The Challenge of War on Poverty to Unfinished Business (19 March 1964).
    New York City Salutes Fifty Years of Service (20 March 1964).
    Poverty Revisited: Challenge to the Urban League (9 April 1964).
    Remarks at Parish Lay Chairmen's Annual Communion Mass and Breakfast, Catholic Charities Appeal (12 April 1964).
    Working Together for Children (Philadelphia) (17 April 1964).
    Working Together for Children (Oregon) (29 April 1964).
    Public and Voluntary Agency Partnership Responsibilities (Notes for Institute--Oregon) (27-29 April 1964).
    The World of Our Children--Working Together for Them (4 May 1964).
    Statement at Colloquy on Training to Serve the Disadvantaged (4 May 1964).
    Statement at Rehabilitation Institute (not delivered in person) (7 May 1964).
    The Social Work Profession and Civil Rights: A Point of View (12 May 1964).
    Statement at Annual Day Care Luncheon (13 May 1964).
    Automation--A Community Responsibility (15 May 1964).
    Notes for Seminar "The City" (20 May 1964).
    Social Implications for Policy and Practice re: Poverty (JRD's Discussant Statement on Norman Lourie's Paper) (25 May 1964).
    A Public Agency's New Approaches to Old Problems (not personally delivered; mailed to Buffalo) (29 May 1964).
    Some Basic Considerations in Social Welfare Planning (11 June 1964).
    Notes on NYC's Plan for the War on Poverty (17 June 1964).
    Social Problems and the Negro Community (17 June 1964).
    Challenges & Expectations in Pakistan: Conference Theme Address by JRD (20 June 1964).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. [part 2], 1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    The Responsibility of the Legal Profession in the War Against Poverty (11 August 1964).
    Planning by Social Agencies (16 September 1964).
    Greer Responds to a Need (3 October 1964).
    Remarks at Foster Family Day at World's Fair (4 October 1964).
    The Effectiveness of Family and Child Welfare Programs for Meeting Problems of Dependency, Neglect and Delinquency (6 October 1964).
    Remarks (Homemaker Service) (8 October 1964).
    Public and Voluntary Agency Partnership Responsibilities (15 October 1964).
    Selected Top Priority Needs for Public Welfare in New York City (16 October 1964).
    The Responsibility of the Mental Health Volunteer in the War Against Poverty (18 October 1964).
    Remarks at Stephen Smith Home (25 October 1964).
    Notes on New York City's Plan for the War on Poverty (27 October 1964).
    Remarks at Annual Day Care Council Meeting (9 November 1964).
    Statement by JRD at Youth Consultation Service FORUM (12 November 1964).
    The Challenge of the Negro Revolution (1 December 1964).
    The Paradox of Poverty (12 December 1964).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. (folder 1 of 2), circa 1964-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Social Welfare (undated).
    Excerpt from Dean's Position Statement on Mission of the Graduate School of Social Service, Fordham University (undated).
    Excerpt from Dean's Proposal for the Organization of the Faculty (undated).
    Reflections of a Dean: Five Years Later (undated).
    Syracuse University Project, School of Social Work, V A Curriculum Building Workshop (27 April 1970).
    N.A.S.W. Speech Re: Historical Perspectives on Social Work (undated).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. (folder 2 of 2), circa 1964-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)